Guide to the Helene Mullins and Marie McCall Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Helene Mullins and Marie McCall papers
1870-1985
1926-1985
YCAL MSS 767
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.46
(4 boxes)
The Helene Mullins and Marie McCall Papers consists of correspondence, writings, and photographs by and relating to the American authors and sisters Helene Mullins and Marie McCall. Correspondence is highly fragmentary, consisting chiefly of letters from Jean and Zohmah Charlot and John Hall Wheelock to Helene Mullins. Photographs depict Mullins and McCall from childhood to later adulthood, and also include portraits and snapshots of family members and friends. Writings include drafts of Mullins's poetry, an autobiographical novel by Mullins entitled The Loving are Daring, and the unpublished diaries of Marie McCall.
Mullins, Helene, 1899-
McCall, Marie, 1909-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Serendipity Books on the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial Fund, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Helene Mullins (1899-1991)
Helene Mullins (née Gallagher), American poet and novelist, was born in New York City in 1899, and was active from the 1920s (by which time she had already married Ivan Mullins) through the 1960s. She and her sister Marie McCall collaborated on their first novel, Paulus Fy (New York: Robert M. McBride & Company) in 1924. Mullins's breakthrough as an author came when a novel, Convent girl, and a volume of poetry, Earthbound & other poems, were published by Harper and Bros. in 1929. In 1935 she was involved in a near-fatal car accident, and soon thereafter she and McCall moved to Hollywood, California, for a lengthy convalescence. Except for this period, and time spent in Washington, D.C., during the Second World War, Mullins lived her entire life in New York City. She continued to publish poems (under the name Mullins, though she later married Linné Johnson) in journals and collected volumes until 1970. Helene Mullins died in Manhattan in 1991.
Marie McCall (circa 1903-1986)
Marie McCall (née Gallagher), American author and painter, date of birth recorded variously as circa 1903 or 1909. Marie McCall and her sister Helene Mullins spent much of their early adulthood living and working together. They collaborated on their first novel, Paulus Fy (New York: Robert M. McBride & Company) in 1924. McCall also published The Evening Wolves (New York: John Day Company, 1949), a novel inspired by Salem witchcraft. Born in New York City, McCall spent much of the latter half of her life in Woodstock, New York, where she died in 1986.
Scope and Contents
The Helene Mullins and Marie McCall Papers consists of correspondence, writings, and photographs by and relating to the American authors and sisters Helene Mullins and Marie McCall. Correspondence is fragmentary, consisting chiefly of letters from Jean and Zohmah Charlot and John Hall Wheelock to Helene Mullins. Photographs depict Mullins and McCall from childhood to later adulthood, and also include portraits and snapshots of family members and friends. Writings include drafts of Mullins's poetry, an autobiographical novel by Mullins entitled The Loving are Daring, and the unpublished diaries of Marie McCall.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Helene Mullins Papers, 1870-1985. II. Marie McCall Papers, 1934-circa 1980.
American literature -- 20th Century; American poetry -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints -- United States -- 20th Century; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Charlot, Jean, 1932-; Charlot, Zohmah; Mullins, Helene, 1899-; McCall, Marie, 1909-; Wheelock, John Hall, 1886-1978
- Series I. Helene Mullins Papers, 1870-1985; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Photographs, and Writings.
  Scope and Contents
  The Helene Mullins Papers consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, and printed material that document the life and work of author Helene Mullins. Correspondence is fragmentary, consisting chiefly of letters from John Hall Wheelock and Jean and Zohmah Charlot. Writings of John Hall Wheelock and of Jean Charlot are filed with their correspondence. Photographs include snapshots and studio portraits of Mullins's parents, of Marie McCall, of the Charlot family, and of other friends, colleagues, and family members, dating from the late nineteenth century through the 1980s. Writings include a typescript draft of an unpublished novel, The Loving are Daring, as well as poems and prospectuses.
  - Correspondence
    - Charlot, Jean, and Zohmah Charlot
      - Catalogue of the Prints of Jean Charlot, printed version, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - What Do You Do With a Book?, by Jean and Zohmah Charlot, proofs, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Jean Charlot Retrospective, printed version, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Obra Pictoria de Jean Charlot, printed version, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - "A Forgotten Novel of American Catholicism," review of Helene Mullin's Convent Girl, typescript, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Letters to Helene Mullins, 1981-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Robinson, Edwin Arlington
      - Letters to Helene Mullins, 1926, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Wheelock, John Hall
      - "Easthampton," poem, holograph, 1928 October (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "The Letter," poem, holograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - "Prayer to the Sun," poem, holograph, and greeting card, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "Silence (in memory of my father)," poem, holograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - "There is a secret...", poem, holograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Letters to Helene Mullins, 1926-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 13-27)
  - Photographs
    - Charlot family, 1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Gallagher family, 1870-1961 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Helene Mullins, 1917-1981 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Marie McCall, 1917-1981 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Paintings by Marie McCall, 1966-1982 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Reception for Helene Mullins, 1970 April 16 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Friends, family, and pets, 1953-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Writings
    Arranged alphabetically by title. Reviews of various works are filed at the end.
    - "Between Two Worlds" (short story), typescript, copy, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "Chronicle of the Lives of Two Sisters" (prospectus for a novel), typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Convent Girl (reviews), typescript, copy, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "Literary Reminiscences (Writers I have Known)" (prospectus for a memoir), typescript, copy, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - The Loving are Daring (novel), typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
    - "Maxwell Bodenheim" (essay)
      - Draft, typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Related clippings and correspondence, 1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "Medical Examination," typescripts, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "Response to Birthday Greeting," (poem), typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "The Sisters" (poem), typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Reviews of writings by Helene Mullins, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Series II. Marie McCall Papers, 1934-circa 1980; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Diaries and Writings. Diaries are arranged chronologically and writings are arranged alphabetically by title.
  The Marie McCall Papers includes diaries of Marie McCall from 1934 to 1977, including some transcripts, a draft of the novel Living Together, and other writings of Marie McCall.
  - Diaries
    Diaries are arranged chronologically, followed by transcripts.
    - Book 41, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Book 44, 1958-58 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Diary, 1977 July-August (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Diary, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Diary, 1985 May-August (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Transcript of letters from "Fred", typescript, 1934, undated (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Transcript of letters from Seamus, typescript, 1934, undated (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Transcript of diary entries, typescript, undated; 3 (Box 3, Folder 54-56)
  - Writings
    Arranged alphabetically by title. Untitled works are filed at the end.
    - Letters to Pop, typescript, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Living Together, typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - The Long Adventure, printed version, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Nathaniel Moleskin and the Chinese Princess and Other Stories, printed, 1931 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - We, typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - We are the Same Life, typescript, 1972 February (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Chapters from and unfinished biography of Louis Eilshemius, typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Notes and clippings, undated; 4 (Box 4, Folder 64-67)
    - Reviews of Marie McCall's writings, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)